Mimicry is when an organism copies
another organism's homework and evolves
to resemble them visually, behaviorally,
chemically, any kind of Lee really. It's
one of the most diverse and useful
traits in nature because the right kind
of deception can mean the difference
between life and death in so many
situations. And today I'm going to
explain them all to you. Let's get into
it. Caterpillars of the eastern tiger
swallow tail have these large black eye
spots that resemble the eyes of snakes.
When birds that normally like to eat
caterpillars see this, they need to take
a moment to decipher whether this is a
tasty morsel or a scary predator. In
order to sell the illusion, the
caterpillar pops out an orange appendage
called an osmaterium, which mimics the
look and smell of a snake's forked
tongue. They also rear up and wriggle in
a way that mimics a lot of predatory
snakes, ultimately scaring the bird
away. This is a case of Batesian
mimicry, the sheep in wolf's clothing.
An intimidation tactic where a prey
animal scares off their predator by
pretending to be something that the
predator would naturally be afraid of.
Cheetah cubs have this layer of white
fur on their back, which looks very
similar to the white mantle of honey
badgers. In case you don't know, honey
badgers might be the single most
dangerous mammal relative to their size.
They are insanely vicious and resilient
and have even been seen going toe-to-toe
with lions and winning. The mere
existence of the honeybger is something
that larger predators need to be aware
of. So helpless cheetah cubs, which are
close to them in size, can take
advantage of this and become a lot safer
when they resemble them. Hence the white
mantle that they lose upon growing up.
Batesian mimicry is the most common and
most studied form of mimicry by far.
Because from an evolutionary
perspective, it's a very simple pathway
to go down. Cheetah cubs that have less
white fur on their back have a lower
chance of being mistaken as a honeybger.
And so they're far more likely to be
targeted by a predator. Meaning that the
ones that are better mimics of their
model species have a better chance of
tricking the dupe species and surviving
to reproduce. It's nice and simple
natural selection. Repeat this cycle for
thousands of years and your species can
become a pretty convincing batian mimic.
Also, yes, it's Batesian, not Bisian,
even though that's how I initially
learned it since it's named after Henry
Bates. But say it however you want. No
one's going to call them mimicry,
please. And now that you understand it,
we have to talk about the one place
where Batesian mimics really shine,
literally. Apostatism is the occurrence
of bright visual patterns across an
animal's surface, causing them to stand
out in their environment. Now, why would
an organism evolve this rather than the
ubiquitously useful camouflage? Well,
it's because they're just being honest.
Aposmatic animals openly advertise that
they are extremely dangerous. Poison
dart frogs are the poster example of
this. They look cute. They look
friendly. But if you ever give one a
kiss, they will not end up a prince.
Instead, you will end up like prince
because these guys are filled to the
brim with enough poison to easily kill a
gorilla or 100 humans. So, now we know
who the real winner of that fight is.
Other good examples of apozeism are the
yellow stripes of bees and wasps, the
iridescent rings of venomous octopus,
and the crazy body shapes of the
flamboyant cuttlefish. Now, aposeism
isn't mimicry. It's an honest signal
that says, "Don't [__] with me." and
gets predators to quickly associate
these bright colors with deadly toxins
or stinky spray or just a disgusting
taste. And so it is the perfect strategy
for mimics to leech off of. These are
different species of Dendrobades frogs
which will kill you with ease. They each
occupy a different geographical region.
And these are members of the species
Dendrobades imitator, a completely
harmless frog that takes on the patterns
of its poisonous cousins depending on
the location that it's in. These are
surfid flies which look like bees and
wasps but are actually pretty friendly
and unable to sting. The cheetah cubs
from earlier are another example of
this. As the reason honey badgers have
their white mantle to begin with is as
an aposmatic signal that advertises that
these paws are rated E for every fauna.
Through bates mimicry, harmless prey can
reap the benefits of deadly animals
without having to do the evolutionary
work of becoming deadly because copying
their outfit is way easier. These are
three different species of snake. One of
them is the harmless milknake. One is
the slightly toxic false coral snake and
one is the coral snake, one of the most
highly venomous creatures in the world.
They each have patterns that consist of
red, white, black, and yellow. But how
do you tell which one is which? Well,
there's the popular adage, red touches
yellow, kill a fellow. Red touches
black, venom lack. Except this saying
can easily get you killed as it only
applies to some areas in North America
and not even 100% of the time.
Apparently, the reason this is so
confusing is that all three of the
snakes are mimics of each other. Sort
of. From the milknake's perspective,
it's just batsian mimicry. It's
harmless. So, it uses the toxic others
as models to appear more threatening.
But from the coral snakes perspective,
it's a bit harder to explain. Because
coral snakes are so deadly, predators
die every single time they try to hunt
them. But because they look like these
other two snakes that predators can
hunt, they still end up getting
attacked. But the whole point of
apoatism is to prevent being attacked in
the first place, which only works when
predators have the opportunity to learn
to stay away. If they're always dying,
they're never learning. And if they're
never learning, the coral snakes are
still getting attacked. So in this case,
it's actually better for the coral snake
to mimic its false counterparts to
receive less attention. It's like they
went overboard with the deadliness to
the point of it being harmful to
themselves. This is called Mc Sllayan
mimicry where a deadly animal mimics a
less deadly one. And this is the only
example of it happening that we really
understand. The only reason it's
possible here is because of the
existence of the false coral snake,
which is the only one that does its job
properly. False corals are toxic enough
that predators will want to avoid them,
but not so toxic that they prevent
predators from learning that, which
allows both the less dangerous milknake
and the more dangerous coral snake to
mimic it. Most systems don't have this
gradient of toxicity to work with, and
so Ms. Sllayan mimicry is unusually
rare. Now, a few organisms have found
that instead of mimicking a more deadly
or less deadly animal, they can pretend
to be the predator itself. Gilbertian
mimicry is Batesian mimicry except the
model and the dupe are the exact same
organism. Pacifllora is a genus of plant
that gets parasetized by heliconius
butterflies. The butterflies lay their
eggs on their leaves which hatch and eat
it up harming the plant. But female
heliconius avoid laying eggs on plants
that they've seen have already been
claimed by another female. Because when
that happens, the families compete for
resources and even cannibalize each
other. So pacifa grows. these small
yellow bumps to deter heliconius
butterflies from laying there.
Gilbertian mimicry is also quite rare
and is only really found in plants. In
animals, it's unlikely that a prey or
host would ever have the means to look
similar to their predator or parasite,
which is obviously a requirement for
mimicry to develop. This is why mimics
and models tend to be somewhat related
or just look similar in the first place.
I mean, caterpillars aren't mimicking
honey badgers because they don't walk,
talk, or look like a honeybger. But they
are often green and tube-shaped, and
they get hunted by birds, which get
hunted by snakes, which are also often
green and tube-shaped. And so, multiple
species of caterpillar have come to look
and act like multiple species of snake.
And not just snakes from their local
area. Remember, this mimicry is meant to
scare away birds. And birds migrate to
other parts of the world during winter.
That means that North American
caterpillars often emulate the behavior
of snakes in the tropics because those
are the snakes that birds typically have
to deal with. An imitation formed from a
hemisphere away. Okay, moving on. We
have malarian mimicry, the only kind of
mimicry that is mutually beneficial to
both model and mimic. Monarch
butterflies tend to be pretty nasty
tasting to a lot of predators. They
signal this aposmatically with their
bright orange wings. Viceroy butterflies
use the exact same strategy. They taste
yucky and signal this with bright wings.
As predators learn to avoid unpalatable
butterflies, a single common warning
signal ends up being recognized. Not
only is it easier for predators to only
have to learn one signal, it's also
better for both butterflies because
fewer will have to die in the process of
the predators learning what to avoid.
So, both species end up mimicking each
other and in this case look almost
indistinguishable. Malarian mimicry is
why both bees and wasps have yellow
stripes. They're both flying insects
that can sting. And because animals
don't want to be stung in general, it
serves them to have similar aposmatic
cues. But far more than two parties can
be involved with this. If there are
several organisms in an area that share
a defense mechanism, they can form a
malarian mimicry ring and all start to
look like each other. We see this with a
variety of bumblebee species as well as
poison frogs and coralnakes. This is
helpful for all the mimics involved, but
it's also helpful for the predators who
can avoid all kinds of dangerous animals
by only recognizing one signal. The only
party it's annoying for is the
biologists who have a hard time
distinguishing between distinct species
that look the same. So, we've seen cases
where the mimic mimics the model, where
the mimic mimics the dupe, even when
multiple mimics mimic each other. Now
it's time for the mimic to mimic the
mimic. Automicimickry is when a mimic
mimics itself or a member of the same
species. This is what the eyes of the
pygmy owl look like. Oh, wait, never
mind. Those are just black spots on the
backs of their heads that appear like a
set of eyes, presumably to ward off
anything that wants to sneak up from
behind. A body part mimicking a
different part. Rubber boas duck their
head beneath their body when threatened
and stick out their suspiciously
headlooking tail. Because a lot of
predators go for the head, misleading
them with a less vital body part can
often buy the boa enough time to escape.
We see this same tactic employed in the
foureyed butterfly fish, which have eye
spots at their tail end and even swim
backwards when threatened to sell the
illusion further. and in hair streak
butterflies, which have a false head at
the back of their wings, as well as
false antenna that move in antenna-like
ways. When scientists collect them, they
often find them with rearwing damage,
suggesting that this strategy actually
works, and predators attack their false
head, allowing them to escape. But you
know where else autom has been used?
Military vehicles. The A10 Thunderbolt
is sometimes painted with a false canopy
on its underside to confuse enemies of
its orientation and obscure the location
of the pilot. Lots of animals have false
eyes like moths, frogs, puffer fish. But
surprisingly, even apex predators have
them, like tigers with eye spots on the
backs of their ears, and orcas, who I
always thought had big white eyes when I
was a kid. So, what exactly do they need
to be afraid of? Well, we don't really
know. Some people think the eye spots
protect them when they're young and just
stay as they grow up. This might make
sense for tigers, whose eye spots are on
full display when they drink from water,
a relatively vulnerable position,
especially for a juvenile. But some
think that eye spots can help with
hunting. It's common for prey animals to
go for the eyes when trying to escape.
And maybe false eyes are there to make
that trickier. I can see this being the
case for orcas whose eyes blend in
readily with their black exterior.
Regardless, there is clearly
evolutionary incentive to have fake eyes
for all sorts of reasons. You would
think that real eyes real eyes real
eyes, but it seems that fake eyes can
trick them quite easily. Now, we also
call it automicry when mimics use
members of their same species as their
model, which can only happen when there
are vast differences within a species.
Monarch butterflies, as we said earlier,
can taste very gross. In fact, blue jays
are often seen vomiting after eating
one. But it turns out to be a bit more
complicated than this. A monarch's
palatability depends on the food that
it's raised on. When monarchs are raised
on cabbage, blue jays tend to find them
quite tasty when they grow up. But when
reared on milkweed, they are absolutely
noxious. And so it serves the cabbage
butterflies to mimic the milkweed
butterflies as much as possible so that
predators don't find out how tasty they
really are. This is called browarian
mimicry and it's basically bates mimicry
just within the same species. This is a
variation of a Churchill tank meant for
recovery rather than offense, but it
mimics an armed variant of the same tank
using a fake dummy gun to scare enemies
into thinking it's more than just an
armored recovery vehicle. Sometimes
entire inflatable dummy tanks have been
used to trick enemies as well. Arguably,
Browarian mimicry is something that
humans do. People act like other people
all the time as a form of mockery or
flattery. We might pretend to be someone
we aren't to attract others or scare
them away. Sometimes we imitate each
other subconsciously, adopting the
phrases and mannerisms we hear from
friends and family or even from TV
shows. But acting like someone else is a
bit different than copying the aposmatic
signals of someone else, right? I mean,
there's a social and personality element
to it that's so uniquely human that it's
kind of hard to call it mimickry in a
biological sense, though acting in
general isn't unique to humans. This
killed deer is flapping one wing because
the other is broken. Wait, did it just
switch which wing is broken? Kill deer
lay their eggs pretty low to the ground,
and when something that it considers a
threat approaches, the mother will act
as if it has a broken wing. This makes
her look like vulnerable prey, taking
the attention off her nest and onto
herself. This kind of behavior was first
noted by Aristotle. I feel like I know
this guy from somewhere. In his history
of animals, he recorded, "When a man
comes by a young brood and tries to
catch them, the henbird rolls in front
of the hunter pretending to be lame. The
man every moment thinks he is on the
point of catching her and so she draws
him on and on until every one of her
brood has had time to escape. Hereupon
she returns to the nest and calls the
young back. And so Aristotellian mimicry
is when an animal imitates some enticing
behavior to distract predators for the
sake of members of its group. Red
squirrels make ventriloquist calls
pretending to be their own young to lead
predators away from their nest. Mento
langers also do this. The male will call
loudly so that the females and children
can hide. Again, it's hard to call this
mimicry. Definitions aren't always
easily agreed upon by different
scientists. And so, usually we just
refer to these behaviors as distraction
displays, which is a whole another topic
worthy of a video itself. But I hope you
can see the similarities to other kinds
of mimicry where deception is cleverly
used for survival. And that leads us to
camouflage, which is kind of like
mimicry, but for the surrounding
environment as a whole, rather than a
specific model organism. But what really
separates the two is the intention.
Camouflage is a form of crypsis, where
the goal isn't to dupe a third party
like in mimicry, but to never be seen in
the first place. That being said, there
exists a perfect intersection between
the two. And when this happens, it's
called mimisis. Leaf insects are
awesome. Stick bugs are cool. The orchid
mantis is one of the most beautiful
creatures on the planet. We also have
these cattydids, which look like
individual leaves. Here's a moth that
specifically resembles a dead leaf.
Pubirds like to stand still with their
heads up and eyes closed in a way that
eerily mimics a broken tree branch.
Also, there are many species of leaf
tailed gecko. Some of them resemble
moss, and some of them, like the satanic
leaf tailed gecko, have entire bodies
that look like leaves. The reason they
were called satanic is probably because
some variations of them are black with
red eyes. Here's a photo I found where
someone put dragon wings on one.
Sometimes organisms mimic non-living
objects for the same reasons, like
pebble plants, which look like stones,
or the caterpillar of the giant swallow
tail, which mimics bird droppings.
Mimisis is like camouflage taken to the
next level. And so, there's not really
much to explain about it. It's just
really cool to show off. But there is
nothing cooler in the world of mimicry
than the mimic octopus. This is a
creature that can change its shape and
color to mimic 18 different marine
animals that we know of and can even
take unique forms on the fly for the
purposes of crypsis or just for fun.
Here's a full list of the animals that
researchers have seen them imitate. But
there are a few main forms that they
seem to take most often. By sprawling
all its arms out radially, the mimic
octopus takes the form of a lion fish,
mimicking its big spines with its arms.
By hiding six of its arms and holding
the other two parallel to each other, it
resembles a sea snake. It even changes
its surface to black and white stripes,
mimicking the aposmatic colors of the
venomous snake. And by tucking all eight
of its arms behind itself and flattening
its main body, it swims around as a
flatfish. Mimic octopus selectively
choose the forms they take depending on
the situation. For example, a researcher
once reported that upon being harassed
by a damselish, the octopus took the
form of a sea snake, a known damselfish
predator. But beyond mimicking set
forms, mimic octopus also possessed the
ability to see something and
intelligently mimic it on the fly, sort
of like a freestyle artist. Because of
this, the mimic octopus really does not
follow the constraints found in other
kinds of mimicry. So, we had to give its
ability a unique name, dynamic mimicry,
which I think should have just been
called shape-shifting because that's
what it is. But yeah, there really is
nothing else like this in nature. We
have to go to fiction to find anything
remotely similar. Okay, have a look at
this spider. Oh, seems like this hungry
bird sees it, too. It flies in to catch
it and Oh, [__] That's not a spider.
That's a whole setup. The spider-tailed
horned viper is probably my favorite
mimic. It has a fake spider tail that it
curls up and moves in a way to mimic the
movements of a real spider. Meanwhile,
it lays the rest of its body perfectly
still, camouflaging with the stone,
waits for a stupid bird, then bam,
dinner is served. See, so far we've
mostly talked about mimicry used for
defensive purposes. But aggressive
mimicry is just as employable. Hey, look
at this beautiful red button that'll
give you a million dollars for free. Oh,
it was actually a subscribe button,
which you should click the real one of
and leave a comment. It helps a lot.
What I just did is a really shitty
version of what the spider-tailed horned
viper does, mimicking something enticing
to lure in prey, only to reveal their
true nature once escaping is no longer
an option. And many of nature's most
ruthless hunters do the same thing. The
alligator snapping turtle sits in a
river, mouth open, wriggling its tongue
around like a worm. It's actually not
its tongue, but an appendage called a
vermapform. But regardless, this
attracts an unsuspecting fish who gets
its existence obliterated once it gets
too close by the 1,000 lb per square in
force of the alligator snapping turtles
bite. Angler fish are known to do this
as well, dangling a fake worm across its
lure to attract a fish, then pop out and
catch it. Turns out we really aren't the
first to invent fishing. In the deep sea
angler fish, instead of a worm, they use
a light. In the darkest of depths,
bioluminescence is the only source of
light, and many smaller organisms use it
for communication and other unknown
reasons. This means that plenty of deep
sea creatures will mistake the angler
fish's lure as something small swimming
around and approach it only to be met
with this monstrosity. But when it comes
to laying traps, few are better than
spiders. Golden orb weavers are named
after their yellow webs, which shine
like gold silks under the sun.
Pollinating insects like bees and flies
follow nectar guides when scouting for
nectar-filled flowers. These can be the
bright colors that flowers often
express, but can also be colors in the
ultraviolet spectrum, which are
invisible to us. The yellow reflective
light that the golden orb weaver's webs
give off can mimic these nectar guides
and cause many pollinators to fly right
into their webs. Other members of the
orb weaver family like the silver argop
add these strange zigzagged structures
called stabilamenta into their webs and
we don't fully know why. At first it was
thought that it helps stabilize the webs
but the stabilamentum tends to be
loosely attached so this probably isn't
the case. Then some scientists noticed
that the way these web decorations are
woven make them really good at
reflecting UV light. When comparing the
position of a stabilamentum in the web
to the regions of bright UV signals in
flower nectar guides, it seems that
these complex weavingings may be an
advanced UV flower mimicry to attract
more pollinators into the orb weaver's
web. Luring prey is evidently very
useful. I mean, as humans, we do it all
the time. But it's also the strategy of
the iconic fantasy monster, the mimic.
By taking the appearance of a bountiful
chest of treasures, dungeon-dwelling
adventurers are enticed by the riches
they could find within, only to be
surprised by a glaring set of teeth or
claws or pseudo limbs or whatever.
Mimicry can be so fun and imaginative
that we often find it in sci-fi and
fantasy media. So the fact that animals
have just been doing it for thousands of
years in real life is pretty cool. There
are other kinds of aggressive mimicry in
nature too. One being wclarian mimicry
or cryptic aggressive mimicry. Blue
streak rass are cleaner fish, meaning
they eat parasites and dead skin off of
larger fish. This is a mutualistic
relationship because it both feeds the
rass and cleans the big fish. This is a
very common trade in the ocean to the
point where large fish visit designated
cleaning stations to get these services.
Kind of like pulling up to a car wash.
When visitors arrive at Blue Streak
Incorporated, the RAS greet their client
by performing a little dance where they
rear up and down. But the Saber-tooth
Blenny takes advantage of all of this by
visually mimicking blue streak cleaner
rass and mimicking their dances to a
regional level. They blend in and the
larger fish doesn't bother to fight them
off. Then they secretly tear off scales
and pieces of fin and even inject the
larger fish with opium to dull the pain
they're causing and give them time to
escape. Wclarian mimicry is the direct
opposite of Batesian mimicry. Instead of
pretending to be intimidating, Wclarian
mimics disguise themselves as harmless
in order to approach their targets
without raising suspicion. They are
wolves in sheep's clothing. The feathers
of the zone tailed hawk look a lot like
that of turkey vultures when they're
flying around. They take advantage of
this fact by flying amongst them, then
swooping out to catch unsuspecting prey.
And to bring up another fantasy example,
Clarion mimicry is kind of what vampires
traditionally do. As monsters
masquerading in human flesh, they will
charm you and invite you to their domain
only to secretly be an undead carnivore.
The saber-tooth blenny is different from
most of the earlier examples because
it's a parasite and not a predator. It
harms its target, but doesn't kill it.
Parasetism as a whole is a very
complicated, disgusting thing. So, you
can imagine when you involve mimicry
with it, it only gets worse. The green
banded brood sack is a flatworm that
parasetizes snails and pulses up and
down their eyetocks. They do this to
mimic caterpillars for the opposite
reason that caterpillars mimic snakes.
The brood sack actually wants to attract
birds because they want their snail
hosts to get eaten. They'll even go so
far as to mind control the snail to move
them out of shaded areas and be more
obvious to spot. Once a bird hunts the
snail, the brood sack is able to infect
the bird and release its eggs into their
poop, beginning the life cycle once
again. Another fascinating example is
the pocketbook muscle, which disguises
its mantle as a fake fish. It wriggles
its fish lure around in a seductive
manner, and when a fish approaches, the
muscle ejects a bunch of its babies into
their mouth. The muscle larae then
attach themselves to the gills, using
the fish's blood as food for several
weeks before dropping off and starting
the cycle a new. But perhaps the most
famous type of parasitic mimicry belongs
to the cuckoo bird, which lays their
eggs in the nests of other birds. Not
only do these eggs mimic that of the
host species, but so does the hatchling,
except the parasitic chick comes
embedded with a devious plan. See, the
cuckoo hatches just a bit quicker than
its step siblings, giving it time to be
fed sooner and grow to be bigger. It
will then go on to bully the others to
get more food for itself. And when mom
isn't looking, it will attempt to throw
the other hatchlings and eggs out of the
nest completely. It's up to the host
parent to recognize this and dispose of
the parasitic child, but that can be
difficult to discern when you're a bird.
Here's a bird feeding what it thinks is
its child, even though it's obviously
grown into a different, much larger
species. Cuckoo bird mimicry is called
Kirbian mimicry, but from the parasitic
side, it's called brood parasetism, the
parasetization of another individual's
parental care. Similar to this is social
parasetism, where a parasite invades a
colony of usocial insects like ants.
Ants have existed for a long time,
leading to very complex organizations
and behaviors, but also complex
relationships with other species.
Animals that integrate themselves with
ants are called mercapiles. And
Merchafilly doesn't have to involve
mimicry, but it often does. And when it
does, it's called Wasmanian mimicry.
Here are some of my favorite examples.
Rove beetles visually mimic ants and
prey on them when they get the chance.
So do many species of spider. The ant
cricket doesn't look like an ant, but
mimics the antenna movements and touch
cues in order to be accepted into the
colony. Large blue caterpillars use
chemical mimicry and release
communication pherommones to trick the
ants into taking them into their nest
and even bring them food. Wasmanian
mimicry doesn't just involve the duping
of one individual, but of an entire
colony. So, while an individual ant is
often the model, the super organism of
all the ants tends to be the dupe. It's
like an alien race disguising itself and
living amongst us without our knowing.
There's honestly so much more to say
about Mccapilic mimics. Wait, Merchilis?
Why? But Merchapili as a whole is just a
really complex thing. It probably
deserves its own video, which I will
probably make someday. Okay, so prey
often use mimicry in a defensive way.
Predators and parasites use mimicry in
an aggressive way. There's one more big
evolutionary reason to use mimicry to
complete the trifecta. This is an
orchid, but it sure looks like a bee. In
fact, it looks so similar that it tricks
bees into having sex with it. This is
called puanian mimicry where plants
mimic an insect to deceive actual
insects into copulating with it so that
the plant itself can copulate by leaving
pollen on its guest. As you know, the
vast majority of flowers offer nectar as
food in order to do this. But puanian
mimics prove that sex sells just as
well. Puyanian mimicry seems to be
primarily done by orchids, which
visually mimic bees and flies and
chemically mimic many of their
pherommones as well. And it's an example
of reproductive mimicry. Mimicry used to
increase the chance of creating
offspring. Oftent times it's only the
male species of a flower that secretes
nectar or pretends to be a sexy bug
because they're the ones that produce
the pollen while female flowers are the
ones that need to get pollinated. So
sometimes female flowers mimic male
flowers in order to ensure that they
actually get visited to complete the
pollination. This mimicry will attract
pollinators that think they'll be
getting nectar only to be ripped off.
This is called biryanian mimicry and
it's a form of interexual automicry.
Contrasting this is the very similar
dodsonian mimicry which is when a plant
mimics a rewarding flower of a different
species for virtually the same reasons.
While the term burian mimicry is
generally reserved for plants, we see a
lot of interexual mimicry in animals as
well. In giant cuttlefish males, being
bigger is generally better. Larger males
can woo females more easily and are able
to bully away smaller males from ever
getting a chance. But this has led to
the smaller males developing a sneaky
cross-dressing strategy. Because of
their small size and the cuttlefish's
ability to make visual adjustments to
themselves, small males can make
themselves pass as female. They use this
to sneak in and quickly mate with a
female, then swim away, all while the
larger male is floating there, thinking
they're just friends, nothing to worry
about. The strategy of smaller sneaker
males pretending to be females is
actually quite common in fish. It
happens in salmon and peacock blennies,
creating a divide where males of a
single species are either exceptionally
large or incredibly small. Another
situation where it's useful for males to
mimic females is in bower birds who are
famous for their complicated branch
structures complete with decorations and
an elaborate dance. Like most creative
practices, coming up with a bower bird
mating ritual requires a lot of
experience and inspiration. So, juvenile
males often learn from adult males who
are already fullyfledged artists. But
adult males in the middle of their
masterpiece don't want any other males
nearby. They want to attract a female.
And so they'll chase other males away,
juvenile or otherwise. Thus, juvenile
male bower birds mimic adult female
bower birds so that they can show up and
learn things from adult males all while
the male begins their mating ritual to
what is actually a teenage boy. In fact,
here's a case where a young bower bird
male disguises himself as a female only
to steal one of the adult males
decorations and fly away with it for
themselves. During the American
Revolutionary War, soldier Robert
Sherliff was shot in the thigh and
sliced across the forehead with a sword.
For some reason, he begged his fellow
soldiers not to take him to a doctor, a
habit he had throughout his entire
military career. But his wounds were too
grave this time. And so, a soldier put
him on his horse and took him to a
hospital. It was only then that the
doctor there discovered his secret. It
turns out Robert Sherliff was a woman
named Deborah Samson who was pretending
to be a man in order to enlist in the
army. She was like American
revolutionary Mulan mimicking a male in
order to do something that at the time
wasn't allowed for a female. Now they
ended up sending her home and she got
married and had kids and wasn't really
recognized for her services until after.
But considering the various sex-based
roles in human culture, both
historically and in the modern day, I'm
sure there have been a myriad more cases
where humans have pretended to be a
member of the opposite sex and engaged
in interexual mimicry. Okay, let's come
back to some plants. Kerrion flowers are
famous for being the stinkiest plants in
the world. I mean, they're called
kerrion or corpse flowers because that's
exactly what they smell like. Many
insects reproduce on decaying bodies, so
they're naturally attracted to the smell
of death. By mimicking this odor,
kerrion flowers lure insects into
thinking they've landed on a good spot
to lay their eggs. But this is a brood
sight deception because the flowers
aren't made of rotten flesh, and so
necroofasages larae don't have anything
to eat here. The corpse flower gains
reproductive potential through this odor
mimicry, though, as they get to leave
their pollen on the insects that they've
tricked into landing. Now, there are far
more aggressive applications of
mimicking reproductive signals as well.
The spotted predatory cattid mimics the
mating calls of female cicas, attracting
male cicas to within its reach to hunt
and eat. This is the only example of
acoustic aggressive mimicry in nature.
When analyzing audio recordings,
scientists found that the same cattids
regularly mimic the calls of cicas from
several different species, including
some from different continents.
Fireflies in the genus furus mimic the
light signals of females in the genus
fotinis to attract male fotinis
fireflies which they kill as prey. We
know that this is done intentionally
because furus females have their own
signals for communication and
reproduction that differ in duration and
delay to the signals they use when
specifically hunting other species of
firefly. This tactic of faking signals
of a sexually receptive female in order
to hunt males of a different species is
called wleakian mimicry. In essence,
it's the same as luring prey, which we
talked about earlier with aggressive
mimicry. The only difference is that
mimics use sexual signals as bait rather
than food. Bola spiders release the sex
pherommones of female moth flies in
order to attract male moth flies. When
they get their prey within range, they
produce a ball of silk and throw it at
them, ins snaring their target in a
ranged attack, just as one would do with
a man-made bola. Unlike the generalist
Catty didids, each species of bola
spider is specialized to a single
species of mothfly, meaning they each
release only the specific pherommones of
their target species. And different bola
spiders don't compete with each other
for the same prey. Oh, and as one more
example, the mimic octopus has been seen
pretending to be a crab looking to mate
in order to approach a crab that it
actually wanted to hunt. And lastly, we
have the one kind of mimicry that was
actually created by humans. Because of
farming, many species of plants have
been labeled annoying wheats, while
others have been seen as useful crops.
Human farmers pull weeds and plant
crops, which has created an
unintentional artificial selection for
the weeds to mimic crops because that
way they can trick the farmers into
replanting them and live for another
year. This is called Vavalovian mimicry
and it's a process that's been going on
since the Neolithic period. Both rye and
oats were originally Vavalovian mimics
of wheat and barley, but at the end of a
growing season, wheat produces seeds
while wild rye doesn't. So farmers would
collect wheat seeds while leaving rye to
die. But eventually some lines of rye
began to show seeds and they duped
farmers into taking them and replanting
them. Amazingly, over the years of
selection, domesticated rye has actually
become usable as a crop we can eat
today. So this is actually a case of a
mimic going fake it till you make it and
transitioning into its own thing. You
may have noticed that other than this
case, humans aren't really involved in
many mimicry systems. We don't overtly
mimic any other species, and no species
really mimics us. That said, there's a
lot that we can learn from mimicry that
we can employ for ourselves. We've
created fake worms to use as bait to
lure prey, just like angler fish and
snapping turtles. If you live in an area
with a lot of deer flies, these fake
dragon flies can actually work at
scaring them away. Scarecrows mimic us
and are meant to deter birds from
getting at our crops. We may not have
mimicry inherently in our evolution, but
we can still make use of it through our
inventions and intelligence. If you
think about the many diverse, cruel
periods in history, how many people hid
their religion, true opinions, or
ethnicity in order to survive and blend
in, just like defensive mimicry, how
many psychopathic murderers fake who
they are to get closer to their victims,
like cryptic aggressive mimicry. Don't
even get me started on what we'll
pretend to be like for reproductive
reasons. Mimicry is all around us, but
it's especially refreshing when you see
that it's also all around the natural
world in starkly different ways. So, I
hope you enjoyed hearing all about it.
Thanks for watching.